here's a visualization of the
intersecting chords theorem
stick around and we'll see a formal
statement of the theorem along with a
visual proof
start with a circle
and draw two chords
inside assume that these two cords
intersect at a point
that then cuts each cord into two pieces
use the two pieces from each cord
as the side lengths of a rectangle
as pictured here
now let's compute the area of these
rectangles
it turns out that no matter how you draw
the chords as long as they intersect the
areas of these two rectangles will be
exactly the same as pictured here
[Music]
the intersecting chords theorem can be
stated as follows
suppose two chords in a circle intersect
at a point dividing one chord into
lengths of a and b and the other chord
into lengths of c and d
then the product a times b equals the
product c times d
let's check out a proof
first construct two triangles by
connecting the chords like this
now there are two angles one in each
triangle subtended by this arc
there's this angle
and this angle
because these angles are subtended by
the same arc they must be congruent
angles
likewise there's an angle in each
triangle subtended by this arc
this one here
and this one in the other triangle
once again because these two angles are
subtended by the same arc they're
congruent
[Music]
but this means that the two picture
triangles that we created are similar
now we can scale the two picture
triangles the top one we can scale by b
and the bottom one we can scale by c and
connect them like this this construction
creates a parallelogram and therefore
the opposite side lengths a times b and
c times d must be equal just as we need
for the intersecting chords theorem
[Music]
you